Inventory of the Louis P. Penningroth papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Louis P. Penningroth papers
1911-1979
93043
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, diaries, memoirs, financial records, reports, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to Young Men's Christian Association aid to Allied prisoners of war in Austria, especially juvenile Russian prisoners; aid to repatriated Russian prisoners at the end of World War I; release of American and British prisoners of war in Russia; and conditions in Russia during the Russian Civil War.
Penningroth, Louis P.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Louis Phillip Penningroth was born in 1889. He was an American clergyman who served as a Young Men's Christian Association worker in Europe from 1915 to 1919. He was interested in providing aid to prisoners of war, especially juvenile prisoners. When he returned home after the war, he married Ethel Blythe, with whom he kept correspondence while in Europe. They had four children and lived in Iowa until Penningroth's death in 1973.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of correspondence, diaries, memoirs, financial records, reports, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs relating to Young Men's Christian Association aid to Allied prisoners of war in Austria, especially juvenile Russian prisoners; aid to repatriated Russian prisoners at the end of World War I; release of American and British prisoners of war in Russia; and conditions in Russia during the Russian Civil War. Of particular note are photographs of Penningroth working in prison camps with prisoners; a personal diary and several account notebooks; Penningroth's manusript writings of his experiences; and personal letters to his future wife detailing his experiences in Europe.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged in two series: Chronological file and Letters to Ethel Blythe
United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; Prisoners of war.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; World War, 1914-1918--Austria.; World War, 1914-1918--Participation, Juvenile.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.; Young Men's Christian associations.
- Chronological file, 1911-1979
  - Diary, 1911 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Young Men's Christian Associations, United States of America, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Booklets and notebooks, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Expense statements and correspondence, 1916 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Photographs of prison camps, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Manuscripts, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Printed material, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Guide for Young Men's Christian Associations Secretaries, 1917 February 24 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Correspondence
    - 1917 January-May (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1917 June (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1917 July (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1917 August (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - 1917 October (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - 1917 November-December (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - 1918 January-March (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1918 April-May (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 1918 June-August (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - 1918 September (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1918 October (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - 1918 November-December (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Photographs of Penningroth, prisoners, and Penningroth's time in Europe, circa 1918 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Writings by Penningroth about helping Russian prisoners of war who had returned to Russia, 1918 June-October (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Russian Constitution, 1918 July 10 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - United States prisoners of war in Camp Rastatt, Germany, 1918 November (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Report of Young Men's Christian Associations work done for Allied prisoners of war passing through Denmark, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Russian prisoners of war in Germany and other countries, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Writings about Russia, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Proposed Young Men's Christian Associations programs, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Russia, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Finances, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - "Required Records,", 1919 January 29 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes correspondence regarding YMCA war prisoner's aid program
  - Correspondence
    - 1919 January (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - 1919 February 1-15 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - 1919 February 16-28 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1919 March 1-9 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - 1919 March 10-31 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1919 April 1-17 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1919 April 18-30 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1919 May (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1919 June (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1919 July-December (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Trip to Russia," writings by Penningroth of rescuing American and British prisoners of war, 1919 March-April (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Records and portrait photographs of released American prisoners, 1919 April (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Released British prisoners, 1919 April (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Conditions in Russia, reports and photographs, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 12-13)
  - Russian relief organizations, 1921 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Clippings about Russia, 1921-1925 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Newspapers, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - The Russian Review, 1926 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - "Russian Story," typescript draft by Penningroth and related newspaper clippings, 1932 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Maps, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Includes map of Russia and map of the main prison camps in Germany and Austria
  - Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Notebooks and clippings, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1915-1979 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Letters to Ethel Blythe, 1917-1919
  Includes original letters and typescript copies
  - 1917 November-December 10 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - 1917 December 11-31 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - 1918 January (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - 1918 February (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 1918 March (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - 1918 April (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - 1918 May (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - 1918 June-July (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - 1918 August-September (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - 1918 October (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - 1918 November (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - 1918 December (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - 1919 January-February (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - 1919 March (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - 1919 April-May (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - 1919 June (Box-folder 5: 13)